A Finding Aid to the Frances Kent Lamont Papers, 1909-1970, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Frances Kent Lamont papers
1909-1970
Archives of American Art
Lamont, Frances Kent, 1899-1975
AAA.lamofran
Archival Resource Key
0.7 Linear feet
The scattered papers of sculptor Frances Kent Lamont measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1909 to 1970. Papers include letters, a school notebook, printed material, two scrapbooks, sketches, and photographs including family snapshots, portraits, and photos of works of art.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The scattered papers of sculptor Frances Kent Lamont measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1909 to 1970. Papers include letters, a school notebook, printed material, two scrapbooks, sketches, and photographs including family snapshots, portraits, and photos of works of art.
Biographical / Historical
Sculptor Frances Kent Lamont (1899-1970) was active in New York, New York. She is known for her war memorials and exhibited extensively in the United States and Europe.
Lamont was born in New York City, but spent some of her childhood in Italy with her father, architect William Winthrop Kent. She studied at the Art Students League and the School of American Sculpture under Solon Borglum upon returning to the United States. In the 1930s, she studied in Paris and exhibited there until the outbreak of World War II. She was a member of the National Sculpture Society. She married Robert Patterson Lamont Jr.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of Frances Kent Lamont were donated in 1975 by Charlotte Austin Kent, the artist's sister.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Sketchbooks; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Women sculptors; Drawings; Women artists; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910
- Frances Kent Lamont Papers, 1909-1970; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes scattered letters from Mrs. Horace Wilson Bennett, Florence Lamont Hinman, Carl Milles, and Boardman Robinson. A notebook labeled "The Bennett School" includes a scholarly paper on anatomy and includes drawings of figures.
  Photographs depict Lamont with her sculpture and sculpting, friends, family, colleagues, and of works of art. Of note is a photo from 1909 of Lamont with Samuel Clemens, "Mark Twain," in Bermuda.
  Printed materials consist of art related publications, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and a theater program for a 1931 production in which Lamont appeared. Also found are two scrapbooks. One dates from 1911 to 1916 and includes autographs of school friends, letters, and handmade holiday cards and birthday greetings. A dismantled scrapbook from circa 1920 to circa 1960 contains records relating to Lamont's sculpting career and includes clippings, letters, and photographs. Signed and unsigned sketches are of figures, animals, children, and objects.
  - Correspondence, 1931-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, Bennett School, circa 1918; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, of Frances Kent Lamont and Friends and Family, 1909-circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, of Sculpture, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, 1931-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
  - Printed Material, Oversized, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1911-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1920-circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Sketches, circa 1920-circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Sketches, Oversized, circa 1920-circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)